<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;

]>

<sect1 id="kernfs" xreflabel="Preparing Virtual Kernel File Systems">
  <?dbhtml filename="kernfs.html"?>

  <title>Preparing Virtual Kernel File Systems</title>

  <para>
    Various file systems exported by the kernel are used to communicate to and
    from the kernel itself. These file systems are virtual in that no disk
    space is used for them. The content of the file systems resides in memory.
  </para>

  <para>
    Begin by creating directories onto which the file systems will be mounted:
  </para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -pv $LFS/dev $LFS/proc $LFS/sys $LFS/run</userinput></screen>

  <para>
    The recommended method of populating the /dev directory with devices is to
    mount a virtual filesystem (such as tmpfs) on the /dev directory, and allow
    the devices to be created dynamically on that virtual filesystem as they
    are detected or accessed. Device creation is generally done during the boot
    process by a program which manages device nodes. Since this new system does
    not yet have any such program and has not yet been booted, it is necessary
    to mount and populate /dev manually. This is accomplished by bind mounting
    the host system's /dev directory. A bind mount is a special type of mount
    that allows you to create a mirror of a directory or mount point to some
    other location. Use the following command to achieve this:
  </para>

<screen><userinput>mount -v --bind /dev $LFS/dev</userinput></screen>

  <para>
    Now mount the remaining virtual kernel filesystems:
  </para>

<screen><userinput>mount -vt devpts devpts $LFS/dev/pts -o gid=5,mode=620
mount -vt proc none $LFS/proc
mount -vt sysfs none $LFS/sys
mount -vt tmpfs none $LFS/run</userinput></screen>

  <para>
    The gid=5 option ensures that all devpts-created device nodes are owned by
    group ID 5. This is the ID we will use later on for the tty group. We use
    the group ID instead of a name, since the host system might use a different
    ID for its tty group. The mode=0620 option ensures that all devpts-created
    device nodes have mode 0620 (user readable and writable, group writable).
    Together with the option above, this ensures that devpts will create device
    nodes that meet the requirements of grantpt(), meaning the Glibc pt_chown
    helper binary (which is not installed by default) is not necessary.
  </para>

  <para>
    In some host systems, /dev/shm is a symbolic link to /run/shm. The /run
    tmpfs was mounted above so in this case only a directory needs to be
    created.
  </para>

<screen><userinput>if [ -h $LFS/dev/shm ]; then
  mkdir -pv $LFS/$(readlink $LFS/dev/shm)
fi</userinput></screen>

</sect1>
