<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;

]>

<sect1 id="network" xreflabel="General Network Configuration">
  <?dbhtml filename="network.html"?>

  <title>General Network Configuration</title>

  <para>
    This section only applies if a network card is to be configured.
  </para>

  <para>
    If a network card will not be used, there is likely no need to create any
    configuration files relating to network cards. If that is the case, you
    will need to remove the network symlinks from all run-level directories
    (/etc/rc.d/rc*.d) after the bootscripts are installed.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Creating Network Interface Configuration Files</title>

    <para>
      Which interfaces are brought up and down by the network script depends on
      the files in /etc/sysconfig/. This directory should contain a file for
      each interface to be configured, such as ifconfig.xyz, where "xyz" is
      meaningful to the administrator such as the device name (e.g. eth0).
      Inside this file are attributes to this interface, such as its IP
      address(es), subnet masks, and so forth. It is necessary that the stem of
      the filename be ifconfig.
    </para>

    <para>
      The following command creates a sample file for the eth0 device with a
      static IP address:
    </para>

<screen><userinput>cat &gt; /etc/sysconfig/ifconfig.eth0 &lt;&lt; "EOF"
<literal>ONBOOT=yes
IFACE=eth0
SERVICE=ipv4-static
IP=192.168.1.1
GATEWAY=192.168.1.2
PREFIX=24
BROADCAST=192.168.1.255</literal>
EOF</userinput></screen>

    <para>
      The values of these variables must be changed in every file to match the
      proper setup.
    </para>

    <para>
      If the ONBOOT variable is set to "yes" the network script will bring up
      the Network Interface Card (NIC) during booting of the system. If set to
      anything but "yes" the NIC will be ignored by the network script and not
      be automatically brought up. The interface can be manually started or
      stopped with the ifup and ifdown commands.
    </para>

    <para>
      The IFACE variable defines the interface name, for example, eth0. It is
      required for all network device configuration files.
    </para>

    <para>
      The SERVICE variable defines the method used for obtaining the IP
      address. The LFS-Bootscripts package has a modular IP assignment format,
      and creating additional files in the /lib/services/ directory allows
      other IP assignment methods. This is commonly used for Dynamic Host
      Configuration Protocol (DHCP), which is addressed in the BLFS book.
    </para>

    <para>
      The GATEWAY variable should contain the default gateway IP address, if
      one is present. If not, then comment out the variable entirely.
    </para>

    <para>
      The PREFIX variable contains the number of bits used in the subnet. Each
      octet in an IP address is 8 bits. If the subnet's netmask is
      255.255.255.0, then it is using the first three octets (24 bits) to
      specify the network number. If the netmask is 255.255.255.240, it would
      be using the first 28 bits. Prefixes longer than 24 bits are commonly
      used by DSL and cable-based Internet Service Providers (ISPs). In this
      example (PREFIX=24), the netmask is 255.255.255.0. Adjust the PREFIX
      variable according to your specific subnet. If omitted, the PREFIX
      defaults to 24.
    </para>

    <para>
      For more information see the ifup man page.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Creating the /etc/resolv.conf File</title>

    <para>
      If the system is going to be connected to the Internet, it will need some
      means of Domain Name Service (DNS) name resolution to resolve Internet
      domain names to IP addresses, and vice versa. This is best achieved by
      placing the IP address of the DNS server, available from the ISP or
      network administrator, into /etc/resolv.conf. Create the file by running
      the following:
    </para>

<screen><userinput>cat &gt; /etc/resolv.conf &lt;&lt; "EOF"
<literal># Begin /etc/resolv.conf

#domain <replaceable>&lt;Your Domain Name&gt;</replaceable>
#nameserver <replaceable>&lt;IP address of your primary nameserver&gt;</replaceable>
#nameserver <replaceable>&lt;IP address of your secondary nameserver&gt;</replaceable>
nameserver 8.8.8.8
nameserver 8.8.4.4

# End /etc/resolv.conf</literal>
EOF</userinput></screen>

    <para>
      The domain statement can be omitted or replaced with a search statement.
      See the man page for resolv.conf for more details.
    </para>

    <para>
      Replace <replaceable>&lt;IP address of the nameserver&gt;</replaceable>
      with the IP address of the DNS most appropriate for the setup. There will
      often be more than one entry (requirements demand secondary servers for
      fallback capability). If you only need or want one DNS server, remove the
      second nameserver line from the file. The IP address may also be a router
      on the local network.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        The Google Public IPv4 DNS addresses are 8.8.8.8 and 8.8.4.4.
      </para>
    </note>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
