<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="xorg7" xreflabel="Xorg-&xorg-version;">
  <?dbhtml filename="xorg7.html"?>

  <title>Introduction to Xorg-&xorg-version;</title>

  <indexterm zone="xorg7">
    <primary sortas="a-xorg7">Xorg</primary>
  </indexterm>


  <para>
    <application>Xorg</application> is a freely redistributable, open-source
    implementation of the <application>X</application> Window System. This
    system provides a client/server interface between display hardware (the
    mouse, keyboard, and video displays) and the desktop environment, while also
    providing both the windowing infrastructure and a standardized application
    interface (API).
  </para>

  <bridgehead renderas="sect3">Xorg Download and Installation
  Instructions</bridgehead>

  <para>
    Xorg-7.0 introduced a completely auto-tooled, modular build system. With the
    new modular build system, it is no longer possible to download the entire
    package in a single file. In fact, there will be well over 100 packages that
    need to be fetched from the download location. To assist with such a large
    task, installing <command>wget</command> is strongly recommended for
    downloading the needed files. A complete <command>wget</command>
    file list is provided for each page that includes multiple packages.
  </para>

  <para>
    Given the number of packages available, deciding which packages you need to
    install for your particular setup may seem a bit overwhelming at first. Take
    a look at
    <ulink url="http://wiki.x.org/wiki/ModuleDescriptions">this page</ulink> and
    <ulink
    url="http://lists.x.org/archives/xorg-modular/2005-November/000801.html">this
    thread</ulink> to get an idea of what you will need. If you are unsure, you
    should install all packages at the cost of extra disk space.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>
      Even if you intend to download only the necessary packages, you should
      download the wget file lists. The list of files are ordered by dependency,
      and the package versions listed in the files are known to work well with
      each other. Further, the wget file lists contain comments for specific
      packages that are deprecated or are not recommended to install. Newer
      packages are likely intended for the next release of
      <application>Xorg</application> and have already proved to be incompatible
      with current versions of software installed in BLFS. The installed size of
      <application>Xorg</application> can be reduced considerably by installing
      only the packages that you will need and use, however, the BLFS book
      cannot account for all dependencies and build options for the individual
      <application>Xorg</application> packages. The instructions assume that all
      packages have been built. A <ulink url="&blfs-wiki;/Xorg7">wiki</ulink>
      page containing dependency information is under development. You are
      encouraged to add to these pages if you discover additional information
      that may be helpful to other users who selectively install individual
      packages.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para>
    Additionally, because of the large number of repetitive commands, you are
    encouraged to partially automate the build. Instructions have been given
    that utilize the <xref linkend="sudo"/> package. It is recommended that you
    use the <parameter>:NOPASSWD</parameter> configuration option for the user
    that will be building the xorg packages.
  </para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Setting up the Xorg Build Environment</title>

    <para>
      Throughout these instructions, you will use the following
      <command>configure</command> switches for all of the packages. Create an
      <filename>/etc/profile.d/xorg.sh</filename> configuration file containing
      these variables as the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>
      user:
    </para>

<screen><userinput role="root">cat &gt; /etc/profile.d/xorg.sh &lt;&lt; "EOF"
<literal>XORG_CONFIG="--prefix=/usr \
             --sysconfdir=/etc \
             --localstatedir=/var \
             --disable-static"
export XORG_CONFIG</literal>
EOF</userinput></screen>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
